Roger Chen

BUSINESS INTELLIGENCE DEVELOPER · CERTIFIED DATA SCIENCE ASSOCIATE · SIX SIGMA YELLOW BELT · M.S. INFORMATION SYSTEMS/DATA ANALYTICS, MATH MINOR

358-405-8438 | **™** rogerchen0418@gmail.com | **™** rogerchen0418 | **™** Website

SUMMARY OF SKILLS

A certified EMC Data Science Associate and seasoned Business Intelligence Developer with 6+ years of experience in building end-to-end BI solutions.

Data Analytics: Tableau, Power BI, SSRS, MicroStrategy, SPSS, SAS Analytics, Google Analytics, SSMS, SSIS, Access, Excel, XLMiner.

Programming: SQL, R, Python, Java, C++, DAX, Power Query, M Query, MATLAB, Visual Basic, VBA, XML.

Other Tools: Salesforce, SAP, Jira, Visual Studio, Lucidchart, Confluence, Smartsheet, SharePoint, PeopleSoft, Oracle Financials, QuickBooks.

BI Functions: ETL, Data Mining, Data Modeling, Data Warehousing, Data Visualization, Dashboards, Ad-hoc Analysis/Reporting, Statistical Analysis.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Business Systems Analyst, Business Intelligence - UC Santa Barbara

Sep 2019 - Present

- Business Intelligence: Revolutionized and automated the department's reporting process by replacing outdated technologies and manual reporting procedures with sustainable and scalable self-service BI solutions. Created and owned 20+ workspaces and apps to support 5 business units with over 40 end-users from AVC to managers. Developed advanced end-to-end data analytics solutions, including data mining, data manipulation, data modeling, data analysis, and data reporting, which enhanced data pipelines, generated actionable insights, and delivered strategic data-driven recommendations, improving process efficiency by 15-25% and saving 100-120 hours and thousands of dollars per month in multiple operations.
- Data Visualization: Developed storytelling reports and dashboards with complex DAX, Power Query, data flows, drill-through, role-level security, and paginated report, delivering elegant, intuitive, and interactive user experience and receiving widespread recognition across departments.
- Governance & Standard: Established report development standards and data governance best practices for data analytics within the department.
- Lean/Agile/Scrum: Adopted Lean and Agile methodologies in BI development and SDLC to improve efficiency, scalability, and collaboration.
- Maintenance and Support: Troubleshot end-user issues, established effective countermeasures, and provided timely resolutions within 48 hours.
- . Mentorship: Mentored analyst interns on the team and shared knowledge to other developers in BI weekly meetings, promoting skill development.

Programmer Analyst – Nortridge Software (Foothill Ranch, CA)

Jul 2017 - Jul 2019

- **Data Analysis:** Led a strategic initiative that analyzed customer behaviors, uncovered potential issues, and made strategic recommendations to remodel the service structure, projecting a 15% decrease in support costs and an 8% boost in customer retention rate.
- System Integration: Gathered business requirements, led the data transfer/ETL process, and integrated a third-party customer support system that enabled the team to serve 18% more customers, reduce the average support ticket time by 13%, and increase customer satisfaction by 15%.
- Consulting Service: Developed customized features and functionalities embedded in the loan software using SQL and VBScript for clients.
- Training & Knowledge Transfer: Created self-help materials in the knowledge base center for business clients and internal employee training.

Business & Technology Analyst, Data Analytics - AXOS Bank (San Diego, CA)

Sep 2016 – Jul 2017

- Risk Analytics: Created KPIs, KRIs, OKRs, key metrics (CAC, LTV, AAR, etc.), and scorecards to recommend the most reliable broker partners to work with and reduce default risk for the TPO team, resulting in a 30% reduction in lead duration and an 18% increase in conversion rate.
- Dashboard Reporting: Designed, developed, and implemented automation dashboards to populate real-time sales and commission data, replacing manual spreadsheet calculation and reporting and saved 20 hours per month.
- Financial Analysis: Developed P&L model, led profitability analysis, and automated financial reports for 12 lending units for senior leadership.
- Budget Modeling: Created budget models that factored historical data from the past 5 years, striving for <10% variance between actual and budget.

Accounting Intern - Big Brothers Big Sisters (Los Angeles, CA)

Jul 2014 - Nov 2014

• General Accounting: Assisted the Director of Finance in A/P, A/R, reconciliation, budgeting, forecasting, financial reporting, and financial analysis.

Case Center Manager – InnoCSR (Shanghai, China)

May 2013 – Aug 2013

- Case Management: Enhanced the Case Center with a 60% increase in case studies and a 50% expansion of the analyst team within 4 months.
- Web Design: Revamped the company's website with a more user-friendly design using WordPress, resulting in a 15% boost in web traffic.

Financial Service Associate – World Financial Group (San Diego, CA)

Dec 2011 – Aug 2012

- Financial Service: Implemented diversification strategies to minimize risk and aim for a targeted annual ROI of 6% for clients.
- Financial Education: Planned and conducted educational seminars and workshops on financial management for clients and prospects.

EDUCATION

Master of Science, Information Systems, specialization in Business Analytics, major GPA 3.7 Computer Science, GPA 4.0

Bachelor of Science, Management Science, minor in Mathematics

Associate of Science, Economics, minor in Accounting

San Diego State University, 2016 San Diego City College, 2014 UC San Diego, 2011 De Anza College, 2009